Preliminary Guide to the Horace Bushnell Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Horace Bushnell papers
1823-1901
MS 1291
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
Letters by and about Horace Bushnell collected by his daughter, Mary Bushnell Cheney in connection with her book: Life and Letters of Horace Bushnell (New York, Harper & Brothers, 1880). The earliest items are a letter from Bushnell's great-grandmother to his mother (n.d.) and a letter to him from his grandmother, Mary Bushnell (1823 June 7). The letters from Bushnell to his daughter, to friends, and to parishioners seeking advice were written between 1855 and 1874. Also in the collection is a marriage service he used. The letters (1876-1901) to Mary B. Cheney concerning her father and commenting on her book, were written by Cyrus Augustus Bartol, Amos Sheffield Chesebrough, N. H. Egleston, Edwin Pond Parker, and William W. Patton who each have essays or letters on Bushnell printed in her book.
Bushnell, Horace, 1802-1876
Immediate Source of Acquisition
In part, gift of Horace B. Learned in 1982.
Biographical / Historical
Horace Bushnell: ordained in the Congregational Church, 1833; pastor of North Church, Hartford, Ct., 1833-1859; author of numerous books; tried and acquitted of heresy, 1850.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Letters by and about Horace Bushnell collected by his daughter, Mary Bushnell Cheney in connection with her book: Life and Letters of Horace Bushnell (New York, Harper & Brothers, 1880). The earliest items are a letter from Bushnell's great-grandmother to his mother (n.d.) and a letter to him from his grandmother, Mary Bushnell (1823 June 7). The letters from Bushnell to his daughter, to friends, and to parishioners seeking advice were written between 1855 and 1874. Also in the collection is a marriage service he used. The letters (1876-1901) to Mary B. Cheney concerning her father and commenting on her book, were written by Cyrus Augustus Bartol, Amos Sheffield Chesebrough, N. H. Egleston, Edwin Pond Parker, and William W. Patton who each have essays or letters on Bushnell printed in her book.
Families; Marriage service; Religion -- 19th century; United States -- Religion; Clergy; Bartol, C. A. (Cyrus Augustus), 1813-1900; Bushnell, Horace, 1802-1876; Cheney, Mary Bushnell, 1840-1917; Chesebrough, Amos S. (Amos Sheffield), 1813-1905; Egleston, Nathaniel Hillyer, 1822-1912; Parker, Edwin Pond, 1836-1920; Patton, William, 1798-1879; Twichell, Joseph Hopkins, 1838-1918
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - Apthorp, Mary, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bushnell, Mary, 1823 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bushnell, Horace (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Letters to his daughter, Mary B. Cheney, 1855 April 13-1874 June 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Letters to others, 1847-1868, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cheney, Mary A. (Bushnell)
      - Incoming correspondence regarding Horace Bushnell and her biography of him
        - Allen, Alexander Viets Griswold, 1901 February 4, 6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - Bartol, Cyrus Augustus, 1876 June 9-1879 August 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - Chesebrough, Amos Sheffield, 1880 June 11-August 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - Egleston, N. H., 1878 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - Parker, Edwin Pond, 1896 February 11 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - Patton, William W., 1880 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - Twichell, Joseph Hopkins, [187?] July 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - Cheney, Mrs. Frank, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Marriage ceremony used by Horace Bushnell [manuscript], undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter to H. B. from congregation and reply, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fragment, 1857-1858 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sermons and addresses, 1831-1859, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letter from A. Bullard, 1847 September 28 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letter from Noah Porter to James Estes, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)